<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" >
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc private="yes"?>
<rfc>
<front>
<title>
Forban Protocol</title>
<author fullname='Alexandre Dulaunoy' surname='Dulaunoy' initials='A. D.'><organization>quuxlabs</organization>
<address><email>a@foo.be</email></address>
</author><date year="2010" month="May"/>
<abstract>
<t>
Forban protocol is a simple Peer-to-Peer (p2p) protocol for local area
network to exchange files. This memo describes the protocol to announce
and discover Peer-to-Peer Forban nodes. As Forban is a Web-based protocol,
this memo includes the convention to reach discovered Forban nodes.</t>
</abstract>
<!-- Use headers in this order #=~-_ -->
</front>
<middle>
<section title="Introduction"><t>
Forban protocol allows users and machines on the same local area network to
share and distribute files. The purpose of the protocol is providing a
simple method to share files without a complex setup on intermittent
local area network.</t>
<t>
The Forban protocol is described in two basic operations:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>
Discovering Forban nodes</t>
<t>
Accessing the discovered Forban nodes</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
The Forban protocol used to announce the Forban nodes is
a simple flooding protocol using UDP messages.</t>
<t>
The Forban nodes serve a Web-based protocol relying on the URL
syntax convention described in this memo.</t>
</section><section title="Applicability Statement"><t>
Forban protocol is intended to function within a local area network where
the number of network nodes is limited (below a thousand of network
nodes).</t>
<t>
The protocol is intended to work on intermittent and mobile network
connectivity using IPv4 or IPv6.</t>
</section><section title="Forban Node Definition"><t>
A Forban node is uniquely defined by an UUID as described in <xref target="RFC4122">
</xref>
.
The UUID MUST be persistent on the Forban node and created
at the first startup of the Forban node. A Forban node MUST be autonomous
from any other network services beside the access medium and the IPv4/IPv6
network used.</t>
<t>
A Forban node SHOULD have a comprehensive name to describe the node.</t>
<t>
A Forban node MAY be connected to more than one network at same time
using different access medium.</t>
</section><section title="Discovery Process"><section title="Announce Message"><t>
An announce message uses the user datagram protocol (UDP) to flood
regularly the network. The message size is limited by the maximum
supported UDP size in IPv4 of 65535 octets minus UDP and IP header.</t>
<t>
The destination UDP port used by default for Forban is port 12555.</t>
<t>
The announce messages are text-based messages. The message is composed
of a single line without CR or CRLF at the end. The message always
starts with a beacon named 'forban;' to detect a Forban message. After
the beacon, there is a key-value list separated by ';'.</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
key = 'name' | 'uuid' | 'hmac'
value = *OCTET
forbanmessage = 'forban;'*(key';'value';')</artwork>
</figure>
<t>
A sample Forban announce message without UDP headers :</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
forban;name;a sample forban;uuid;d55727ed-5c6a-49a8-9d8d-28b4004aee0c;hmac;9bc2974df7325cd0ecf517c572fe20859aa2c228</artwork>
</figure>
</section></section><section title="Access Process"><t>
Forban web-based service MUST use the same port number allocated by
the Forban UDP announce message. As the URL is built based
on the destination port used in the announce, the TCP web-based services
MUST share the same port.</t>
<section title="Base URL"><t>
In Forban, the URL to access a Forban is composed by using the announce
message. The URL format is the following constructed with the source
IP of the Forban announce message and the destination port used.</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
http://[source]:[port]/</artwork>
</figure>
</section><section title="Index URL"><t>
The index URL is used to fetch the index of the Forban and MUST be present.
The index URL is a composed of the base URL plus a specific path :</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
http://[baseurl]/s/?g=forban/index</artwork>
</figure>
</section><section title="Fetch URL"><t>
The fetch URL is used to fetch a specific file from a Forban and
MUST be present. The
fetch URL is composed of the base URL plus a specific path including
the filename of the file name in Base64 ursafe :</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
http://[baseurl]/s/?g=base64_urlsafe(&lt;filenamefromindex&gt;)&amp;f=b64e</artwork>
</figure>
</section></section><section title="Notation Conventions"><t>
The capitalized key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
&quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and
&quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">
</xref>
.</t>
</section><section title="Terminology"><t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>
Forban node - is local area network device supporting the Forban protocol as described in this memo</t>
<t>
Forban index - is the index of files proposed by a Forban node</t>
</list>
</t>
</section><section title="Editorial Notes"><t>
To provide feedback on this draft join the Forban
mailing list at
<eref target="http://groups.google.com/group/forban">http://groups.google.com/group/forban</eref></t>
</section><section title="References"></section></middle>
<back>
<references>

<reference anchor='RFC2119'>

<front>
<title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year='1997' month='March' />
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
<format type='TXT' octets='4723' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='17491' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='5777' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
</reference>
Bradner, S., &quot;Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels&quot;, BCP 14, RFC 2119, March 1997.
<reference anchor='RFC4122'>

<front>
<title abbrev='UUID URN'>A Universally Unique IDentifier (UUID) URN Namespace</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Leach' fullname='Paul J. Leach'>
<organization>Microsoft</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1 Microsoft Way</street>
<city>Redmond</city>
<region>WA</region>
<code>98052</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 425-882-8080</phone>
<email>paulle@microsoft.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Mealling' fullname='Michael Mealling'>
<organization>Refactored Networks, LLC</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1635 Old Hwy 41</street>
<street>Suite 112, Box 138</street>
<city>Kennesaw</city>
<region>GA</region>
<code>30152</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1-678-581-9656</phone>
<email>michael@refactored-networks.com</email>
<uri>http://www.refactored-networks.com</uri></address></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Salz' fullname='Rich Salz'>
<organization>DataPower Technology, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1 Alewife Center</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02142</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 617-864-0455</phone>
<email>rsalz@datapower.com</email>
<uri>http://www.datapower.com</uri></address></author>
<date year='2005' month='July' />
<keyword>URN, UUID</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>This specification defines a Uniform Resource Name namespace for
      UUIDs (Universally Unique IDentifier), also known as GUIDs (Globally
      Unique IDentifier). A UUID is 128 bits long, and can
      guarantee uniqueness across space and time. UUIDs were originally
      used in the Apollo Network Computing System and later in the Open
      Software Foundation's (OSF) Distributed Computing Environment (DCE),
      and then in Microsoft Windows platforms.</t>
<t>This specification is derived from the DCE specification with the
      kind permission of the OSF (now known as The Open Group).  Information from earlier versions of the DCE specification have been	
      incorporated into this document.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4122' />
<format type='TXT' octets='59319' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4122.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='82717' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc4122.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='62931' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc4122.xml' />
</reference>
Leach, P., Mealling, M., and R. Salz, &quot;A Universally Unique IDentifier (UUID) URN Namespace&quot;, RFC 4122, July 2005.</references>
</back>
</rfc>
